# Global Rules for Windsurf / Cascade

## Meta Rule
When applying rules, briefly state which rule category you're following 
at the start of your response. Example: "[Code Quality] Applying 
immutability and early-return patterns."

---

## 1. Behavior & Decision Making

- **Plan before you code.** For any task involving more than one file, 
  describe your approach first and wait for confirmation before making changes.
- **Never hallucinate APIs, libraries, or functions.** If you're unsure 
  whether a method exists, say so explicitly. Do not guess.
- **Ask, don't assume.** If the task is ambiguous, ask one focused 
  clarifying question before proceeding.
- **Minimal footprint.** Only touch files directly relevant to the task. 
  Do not refactor unrelated code unless explicitly asked.
- **No unsolicited rewrites.** If you spot issues outside the scope of 
  the task, report them as a note — do not fix them without permission.
- **Prefer existing patterns.** If the codebase already solves a problem 
  a certain way, follow that pattern unless asked to change it.

---

## 2. Source of Truth Hierarchy

When information conflicts, resolve it in this order:
1. Explicit user instruction in the current session
2. `.windsurfrules` (project-level)
3. Actual code behavior (runtime/test results)
4. This global rules file
5. Official library documentation

Never trust comments or outdated documentation over actual code behavior.

---

## 3. Code Quality Standards

- **TypeScript strict mode** — all new code must be fully typed, no `any` 
  unless absolutely unavoidable and explicitly noted
- **Early returns** over deeply nested conditionals
- **Pure functions** where possible; side effects must be explicit
- **Meaningful names** — variables, functions, and components must be 
  self-documenting; avoid abbreviations
- **No magic numbers** — use named constants
- **DRY but not over-abstracted** — don't abstract until you see the 
  pattern used 3+ times
- **Error handling is not optional** — every async function must handle 
  errors explicitly

---

## 4. File & Commit Hygiene

- Never delete files without explicit instruction
- Never modify `.env`, config files, or secrets without explicit instruction
- One logical change per commit; conventional commit format:
  `feat:`, `fix:`, `refactor:`, `chore:`, `docs:`, `test:`
- Always add/update relevant JSDoc or inline comments for 
  non-obvious logic

---

## 5. Communication Style

- Be direct and concise — no filler phrases like "Certainly!" or 
  "Great question!"
- When presenting options, give a clear recommendation with reasoning
- Flag risks or potential side effects explicitly
- If a task will take many steps, provide a numbered plan upfront
